<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yushurchen.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yushurchen.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-18T01:12:45+00:00</updated><id>https://yushurchen.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yu-Shu Chen</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">on how I come to what I believe</title><link href="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-think/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on how I come to what I believe"/><published>2025-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-think</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-think/"><![CDATA[<p>Before I begin, I want to define these words as I’m using them in this post, just for clarity here, since people might use them differently elsewhere. These are based on Merriam-Webster but adapted slightly:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Thought</strong>: a product of thinking — a momentary mental reflection or consideration. Thoughts can be fleeting and unstructured.</li> <li><strong>Idea</strong>: a formulated thought — more developed and structured, often something that can be examined or evaluated. Ideas can be thoughts one comes up with or come from other people’s beliefs.</li> <li><strong>Belief</strong>: something one holds to be true, at least tentatively — a more stable position formed after some evaluation or reasoning.</li> </ul> <hr/> <p>Like everyone else, I have pre-existing beliefs. When I encounter a new idea, I go through a process before accepting or rejecting it.</p> <p>The process follows the scientific method: <strong>observe</strong>, <strong>identify problem</strong>, <strong>research</strong>, <strong>experiment (reasoning &amp; evidence)</strong>, <strong>conclude</strong>. Importantly, new ideas must be supported by stronger reasoning or better evidence than what I believe in order for me to update my beliefs. This mirrors the burden of proof in philosophy and the roles of the null and alternate hypotheses in statistics: the default position stands unless a stronger alternative emerges.</p> <p>This process matters for more than just figuring out what’s true or false. The scientific method represents a disciplined way of thinking—one grounded in structured curiosity, logical consistency, and a willingness to revise. While we often associate it with empirical science, it’s just as relevant to philosophy, ethics, and personal reflection. Even when we’re dealing with concepts that can’t be measured in a lab, we can still question assumptions, evaluate internal coherence, and adjust our views over time. Philosophy, in that sense, isn’t separate from science—it’s a domain that follows the same spirit. Thoughtful, structured reasoning is how we make progress, regardless of the topic. It’s not just about having the right answers, but about asking better questions—and being ready to change when the answers surprise us.</p> <p>One key point is that this broader process does not prove things to be absolutely true or false. It relies on evidence and observation to support or refute hypotheses and theories, all of which are open to revision when new information emerges. That’s why beliefs, even well-reasoned ones, must remain open to change. Holding beliefs too tightly, without leaving room for better ideas, undermines the entire process of growth and understanding. In addition, just because I don’t hold a belief, or even disagree with it, doesn’t mean I can’t understand or sympathize with it. Part of evaluating ideas fairly means engaging with them on their own terms, not just defending my own position.</p> <p>If you have a different view on how we should come to believe what we do, I’d love to hear from you. I’ll apply the same process and see where it leads me.</p> <p>Hope you enjoyed reading my first post!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Before I begin, I want to define these words as I’m using them in this post, just for clarity here, since people might use them differently elsewhere. These are based on Merriam-Webster but adapted slightly:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">on the purpose of this blog</title><link href="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/purpose-of-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on the purpose of this blog"/><published>2025-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/purpose-of-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/purpose-of-blog/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog is meant to document what I think on various topics, and help me develop writing skills (a very minor part of the purpose). I aim to keep posts short and straightforward for ease of reading. I’m not a great (nor fast) writer (yet) and it usually takes me a long time to write something before I am satisfied with it, but I sometimes don’t have the time or patience to sit down and write for a long time, so you may feel like some posts have lots of unorganized ideas or the writing aren’t great (this post is meant to be a demonstration of what that may look like). I’ll come back and make sure it’s there when I have time (which is never, lol. jk). I sometimes use writing tools like ChatGPT and Grammarly to help with grammar and phrasing, especially when I revisit posts to clean them up.</p> <p>If my thoughts on a topic change, my current plan is to cross out things that no longer apply (not delete) and add in new thoughts. This is not only to keep track of how my thoughts changed but also to keep me from making statements that I may regret later on (not that I usually do).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog is meant to document what I think on various topics, and help me develop writing skills (a very minor part of the purpose). I aim to keep posts short and straightforward for ease of reading. I’m not a great (nor fast) writer (yet) and it usually takes me a long time to write something before I am satisfied with it, but I sometimes don’t have the time or patience to sit down and write for a long time, so you may feel like some posts have lots of unorganized ideas or the writing aren’t great (this post is meant to be a demonstration of what that may look like). I’ll come back and make sure it’s there when I have time (which is never, lol. jk). I sometimes use writing tools like ChatGPT and Grammarly to help with grammar and phrasing, especially when I revisit posts to clean them up.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">on what I mean by _____</title><link href="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/what-i-mean/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on what I mean by _____"/><published>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/what-i-mean</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yushurchen.github.io/blog/2025/what-i-mean/"><![CDATA[<p>Although these words and phrases are commonly used and have well-established definitions, I want to ensure that readers understand exactly what I mean when I use them, so there is no ambiguity. In this post, I’ll share not only what I mean by each word or phrase but also what I do not mean, along with examples to clarify their intended use.</p> <p>These definitions will be added and refined over time as I publish more posts. Unless a specific post provides its own definition, the meanings here apply to all posts.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Although these words and phrases are commonly used and have well-established definitions, I want to ensure that readers understand exactly what I mean when I use them, so there is no ambiguity. In this post, I’ll share not only what I mean by each word or phrase but also what I do not mean, along with examples to clarify their intended use.]]></summary></entry></feed>